Welcome back to One New Section, in which we will talk about the computer network.
How it is, how it communicated from one source to another source, one end-wise to another
end-wise, let's see.
What is a network?
At its core, a computer network is simply a collection of two or more interconnected
computer.
These connections can be established using either physical cable.
You can use a wired cable, a carrier 6, a ultra 40 wire, which is used to connect from
a desktop to ethernet port for internet or electromagnetic waves, a wireless, which now this
is from access point or router.
You have in your house, you have a router, a Wi-Fi router, which is providing you internet
through a wireless network, electromagnetic waves, forming the backbone of modern
desktop communication.
My modern desktop communication, because now the physical cables or wired cables have
more, we can say, capabilities are providing a fast and reliable internet, a more GPS, more
key cup pits, more GPS internet, we can now take through a wired network for a longer
distance.
In an electronic way, wireless, we have at any point of our house, but we can communicate
to our network, we can, we have that internet, in our phone, okay.
To link the devices and enable data exchange network live on combination of specializations,
hardware and software, a diverse range of nodes can be a part of computer network product.
Here, nodes means end devices, end devices can be a computer laptop mobile, whatever it
is, a wireless printer, a wireless, your electronic any devices, your Alexa, so these are
the nodes here, okay.
Now what are the part of the computer, it can be server, it's providing you have any
type of service, okay, a server, a file server, a mouse or whatever, any type of server,
networking hardware, router, switches, repeater, a router is the one that providing you the
first information, sending any data packet, you want any, you request any type of information
to Chrome.
Now it's going back to Chrome to data center and from there, it is giving you that information
firstly, router is the one that keeps routing, routing path to our data, switches.
So the play we don't have switches in our house, but we have in a corporate, in a companies,
so data will be intelligent switches as well, we will talk on this and networking hardware,
we have rapid as well, in some houses like a good house, we can show up people who have
good money, so what they use, they use rapid, they have Wi-Fi, wireless router, now
a router, at some day after some distance, their wireless connectivity, their wireless
strength of their internet, of their Wi-Fi, getting weaker and weaker, so repeater
plays there to increase the strength of their connection of their wireless connection,
so for that, they using network hardware, then there's a personal computer, there's a text
of a laptop, I just said earlier, and other specializer is an approach to resist.
Now, exploding network types, wired or wireless network, wired network address, physical
networks, corporate, repair or fiber, optics, rolling devices to internet or other network,
no for high security, due to physical connection, generic bandwidth, location for each user,
where the little signal delay and high reliability, ideal for a specific phase, user,
corporate, recurring robust, secure connection, wireless network, wireless network, operate
without physically physical troubles, using electromagnetic or informative wave for connectivity,
provide, freedom of movement, ease of deployment, example, circular phone, Wi-Fi devices,
TV remote, lower installation cost, yes, while offering flexibility, wireless networks
generally have lower security and higher latency compared to wired network connection, yes,
because they have no wireless security as well, so this is the thing that is we have to
notice, but in wired network, in which we use a cable, okay, so of course, provide a high
security due to physical connection is there, and the packed with allocation to each user is increased.
Okay, now, very little signal delay and high reliability, it is always always as you,
these are common sense, if you're using wireless or wired, wired gives you better stability.
However, if you win a company, then there's more chances that every user, every user,
ask you to provide a wired Ethernet cable to them. Now, let's talk about the difference,
wired wireless, though you don't have to remember just visualize, it is a wired, so it is a fast,
so and as the same time, there's a low delay, low propagation threshold, low latency,
as a wired, it is more secure and reliable, as a wired device, which is using this wired should be
have that port, okay, so device must be hardwired, but as it is a wired, it is an expensive as well,
and for every device, you have to put a cable, so it's a higher installation and maintenance cost,
and at the same time, you cannot increase a number of users, because you have limited port in your
access switch, you have limited port in your text, so scalability is not that possible. However,
a wireless is a good future of reading scope, okay, in upcoming 10 years, every company is going to
use wireless network, there is no dependency on wired network, because it cost much higher in wireless
network, every user gets physicality to move from one place to another place and have their intent
connected at the same time, it's low cost, next move ahead, so this is how it works, when wireless
network, you can see a wifi sign and a Bluetooth which is also wireless network, now what is a cloud
computing? cloud computing is an internet-based model where shared computing resources hardware
software services are provided on demand, this resources are decided in physical data center
managed by cloud service provided globally, it offers quick access to scalable computing
resources with minimal management, but there are four primary type of cloud, the program model,
so basically everything is in a cloud, so you are in a home, you access your toy, system your
access your files, it resources everything from a cloud you don't depend on your corporate office,
okay, so you don't have to go on your office to get those files or to get a file server,
your file server is in a cloud, you can access from anywhere if you have internet, okay,
now type of cloud public, everyone can see every accessible to everyone over the internet
on or created by third-party provider, many over the second order to open us, microsoft as your
Google attention this, then we have private and hybrid, private for an organization, a single
organization can be owned, managed and operated by organization third party or above, because
it is not easy to manage a cloud, okay, so what the company do is, we use the third party
over and over, which you use, which maintain that cloud, in behalf for that company, okay,
so this is how it works, EBA, and then there is a hybrid cloud, many company work on hybrid,
when the thing which are not important, they put on on a, they're in corporate office
with their local server, so that they can reduce the cost, because if you're doing that
following your cloud, you have to pay, you have to decide to reduce that cost, they put that
in a your corporate local server, okay, or local cloud, a blend of more cloud models,
combine the strength of each model, offering stability, cost of each data security, the main
challenges, as it's completely set up, now, community cloud, it is one of the best, every, like,
every day, where, before company is very big, you're going to do with it, okay,
cloud infrastructure, shared amongst several organizations with common concerns or
requirement can hosted on-premise or by a third party, there's a budget participating organization
on a third party, okay, so every cloud, the tech has their pros, cons, depend on your company
requirement, depend on the security, what, depend on the cost you have, the budget you have,
the scalability you want, you have, it on that, you decide which cloud model you have to move on,
okay, now, you have to understand some protocols, so if you're connected to an internet,
it either TCP, you to be, TCP connection is the one, that is connection oriented,
a connection oriented means, once the connection established, it will not break, and if we break,
then TCP is the one or TCP is more level, so that if you send data from one system to another
system through TCP, TCP will ensure that, yes, the model, the data should lead to another system,
while in UDP, it can be, it not be, it not at reliable, so we use video call, a zoom call,
a goal made, whatever it is, in that sometime you see that people speak something but you
not listen about, you miss that, because it's on UDP, it's not reliable, however a TCP is more
reliable, you send a file, you send a message in your WhatsApp to another user, it makes
sure that WhatsApp send this message to another, okay, so it give you guaranteed that it will
the reach, now, other after when they get internet, it will reach, so TCP idle for web browsing,
because if you're going to enter a google.com, it will go to the document, okay, so it's for
Google browsing or email, wait data, intake days, where am I, okay, while in the UDP is used for gaming,
video streaming, meeting, that speed is protest over current delay, FTP was it, they have to be,
I'm just telling you this one, too, you have to get that this type of protocols we have,
no, FTP uses TCP to transfer file between client and server, yes, because you can't
say that some files can go some files can't, you have to make it so that a profile
is moved from one to another place, so FTP use TCP or offer robust feature like authentication
and direct navigation, direct navigation is to make so that where the files should be stored,
a travel file transfer, simple UDP base protocol for file transfer, it is a pattern version
after you have to be, look, lack authentication is there and error checking, but it is used for
voting networking device, okay, so this is how we use protocols, okay, this particular fundamental
to how network function ensuring diverse application can communicate effectively, so it's all
dependent on your, as you move to network, depending on your case, depending on your things,
you have to decide which protocol you have to use, which topology you have read,
which network you have to use, which wireless-award way to method to use is all dependent on that,
thank you very much, we will connect on the next section and share this course with your
brothers from one another. Thank you, bye bye.